<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-opsawg-add-encrypted-dns-09"
     ipr="trust200902" updates="4014">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="RADIUS DHCP-Options">RADIUS Extensions for DHCP Configured
    Services</title>

    <author fullname="Mohamed Boucadair" initials="M." surname="Boucadair">
      <organization>Orange</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Rennes</city>

          <region></region>

          <code>35000</code>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>mohamed.boucadair@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Tirumaleswar Reddy" initials="T." surname="Reddy">
      <organization>Nokia</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city></city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>kondtir@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Alan DeKok" initials="A." surname="DeKok">
      <organization>FreeRADIUS</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city></city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country></country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <facsimile></facsimile>

        <email>aland@freeradius.org</email>

        <uri></uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date />

    <workgroup>opsawg</workgroup>

    <keyword>redirection</keyword>

    <keyword>subscriber policies</keyword>

    <keyword>differentiated service</keyword>

    <keyword>DNS</keyword>

    <keyword>DoH</keyword>

    <keyword>DoT</keyword>

    <keyword>DoQ</keyword>

    <keyword>QUIC</keyword>

    <keyword>Encryption</keyword>

    <keyword>Service delivery</keyword>

    <keyword>Service provisioning</keyword>

    <keyword>service activation</keyword>

    <keyword>policies</keyword>

    <keyword>connectivity</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document specifies two new Remote Authentication Dial-In User
      Service (RADIUS) attributes that carry DHCP options. Even if the
      specification was initially motivated by the configuration of encrypted
      DNS resolvers, the specification is generic and can be applicable to any
      service that relies upon DHCP. Both DHCPv4 and DHCPv6 configured
      services are covered.</t>

      <t>Also, this document updates RFC 4014 by relaxing a constraint on
      permitted RADIUS Attributes in the RADIUS Attributes DHCP suboption.<!--
--></t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>In the context of broadband services, Internet Service Providers
      (ISPs) usually provide DNS resolvers to their customers. To that aim,
      ISPs deploy dedicated mechanisms (e.g., DHCP <xref
      target="RFC2132"></xref> <xref target="RFC8415"></xref>, IPv6 Router
      Advertisement <xref target="RFC4861"></xref>) to advertise a list of DNS
      recursive servers to their customers. Typically, the information used to
      populate DHCP messages and/or IPv6 Router Advertisements relies upon
      specific Remote Authentication Dial-In User Service (RADIUS) <xref
      target="RFC2865"></xref> attributes, such as the DNS-Server-IPv6-Address
      Attribute specified in <xref target="RFC6911"></xref>.</t>

      <t>With the advent of encrypted DNS (e.g., DNS-over-HTTPS (DoH) <xref
      target="RFC8484"></xref>, DNS-over-TLS (DoT) <xref
      target="RFC7858"></xref>, or DNS-over-QUIC (DoQ) <xref
      target="RFC9250"></xref>), additional means are required to provision
      hosts with network-designated encrypted DNS. To fill that void, <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-add-dnr"></xref> leverages existing protocols such as
      DHCP to provide hosts with the required information to connect to an
      encrypted DNS resolver. However, there are no RADIUS attributes that can
      be used to populate the discovery messages discussed in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-add-dnr"></xref>. The same concern is likely to be
      encountered for future services that are configured using DHCP.</t>

      <t>This document specifies two new RADIUS attributes: DHCPv6-Options
      (<xref target="v6"></xref>) and DHCPv4-Options (<xref
      target="v4"></xref>) Attributes. These attributes can include DHCP
      options that are listed under the IANA registries that are created in
      Sections <xref format="counter" target="drv6-reg"></xref> and <xref
      format="counter" target="drv4-reg"></xref>. These two attributes are
      specified in order to accommodate both IPv4 and IPv6 deployment contexts
      while taking into account the constraints in <xref section="3.4"
      target="RFC6158"></xref>.</t>

      <t>The mechanism specified in this document is a generic mechanism and
      might be employed in network scenarios where the DHCP server and the
      RADIUS client are located in the same device. The new attributes can
      also be used in deployments that rely upon the mechanisms defined in
      <xref target="RFC4014"></xref> or <xref target="RFC7037"></xref>, which
      allow a DHCP relay agent that is collocated with a RADIUS client to pass
      attributes obtained from a RADIUS server to a DHCP server. However, an
      update to <xref target="RFC4014"></xref> is required so that a DHCP
      relay agent can pass the DHCPv4-Options Attribute obtained from a RADIUS
      server to a DHCP server (<xref target="RAD"></xref>).</t>

      <t>DHCP options that are included in the new RADIUS attributes can be
      controlled by a deployment specific policy. Discussing such a policy is
      out of scope.</t>

      <t>This document adheres to <xref target="RFC8044"></xref> for defining
      the new attributes.</t>

      <t>A sample deployment usage of the DHCPv6-Options and DHCPv4-Options
      RADIUS attributes is described in <xref target="sample"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14
      <xref target="RFC2119"></xref> <xref target="RFC8174"></xref> when, and
      only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>

      <t>This document makes use of the terms defined in <xref
      target="RFC2865"></xref>, <xref target="RFC8415"></xref>, and <xref
      target="RFC8499"></xref>. The following additional terms are used: <list
          style="hanging">
          <t hangText="DHCP:">refers to both DHCPv4 <xref
          target="RFC2132"></xref> and DHCPv6 <xref
          target="RFC8415"></xref>.</t>

          <t hangText="Encrypted DNS:">refers to a scheme where DNS exchanges
          are transported over an encrypted channel. Examples of encrypted DNS
          are DoT, DoH, and DoQ.</t>

          <t hangText="Encrypted DNS resolver:">refers to a resolver (<xref
          section="6" target="RFC8499"></xref>) that supports encrypted
          DNS.</t>

          <t hangText="DHCP*-Options:">refers to DHCPv4-Options and
          DHCPv6-Options Attributes (<xref target="att"></xref>).</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="att" title="DHCP Options RADIUS Attributes">
      <t>This section specifies two new RADIUS attributes for RADIUS clients
      and servers to exchange DHCP-encoded data. This data is then used to
      feed the DHCP procedure between a DHCP client and a DHCP server.</t>

      <t>Both DHCPv4-Options and DHCPv6-Options Attributes use the "Long
      Extended Type" format (<xref section="2.2" target="RFC6929"></xref>).
      The description of the fields is provided in Sections <xref
      format="counter" target="v6"></xref> and <xref format="counter"
      target="v4"></xref>.</t>

      <t>These attributes use the "Long Extended Type" format in order to
      permit the transport of attributes encapsulating more than 253 octets of
      data. DHCP options that can be included in the DHCP*-Options RADIUS
      attributes are limited by the maximum packet size of 4096 bytes (<xref
      section="3" target="RFC2865"></xref>). In order to accommodate
      deployments with large DHCP options, RADIUS implementations are
      RECOMMENDED to support a packet size up to 65535 bytes. Such a
      recommendation can be met if RADIUS implementations support a mechanism
      that relaxes the 4096 bytes limit (e.g., <xref target="RFC7499"></xref>
      or <xref target="RFC7930"></xref>).</t>

      <t>The value fields of DHCP*-Options Attributes are encoded in clear and
      not encrypted as, for example, Tunnel-Password Attribute <xref
      target="RFC2868"></xref>.</t>

      <t>RADIUS implementations may support a configuration parameter to
      control the DHCP options that can be included in a DHCP*-Options RADIUS
      attribute. Likewise, DHCP server implementations may support a
      configuration parameter to control the permitted DHCP options in a
      DHCP*-Options RADIUS attribute.</t>

      <t>For ease of administrator configuration, the RADIUS server SHOULD
      expose the DHCP options and allow administrators to configure them,
      instead of requiring them to be entered as opaque data.</t>

      <t>RADIUS supplied data is specific configuration data that is returned
      as a function of authentication and authorization checks. As such,
      absent any explicit configuration on the DHCP server, RADIUS supplied
      data by means of DHCP*-Options Attributes take precedence over any local
      configuration.</t>

      <t>These attributes are defined with globally unique names. The naming
      of the attributes follows the guidelines in Section 2.7.1 of <xref
      target="RFC6929"></xref>.</t>

      <section anchor="v6" title="DHCPv6-Options Attribute">
        <t>This attribute is of type "string" as defined in <xref
        section="3.5" target="RFC8044"></xref>.</t>

        <t>The DHCPv6-Options Attribute MAY appear in a RADIUS Access-Accept
        packet. It MAY also appear in a RADIUS Access-Request packet as a hint
        to the RADIUS server to indicate a preference. However, the server is
        not required to honor such a preference.</t>

        <t>The DHCPv6-Options Attribute MAY appear in a RADIUS CoA-Request
        packet.</t>

        <t>The DHCPv6-Options Attribute MAY appear in a RADIUS
        Accounting-Request packet.</t>

        <t>The DHCPv6-Options Attribute MUST NOT appear in any other RADIUS
        packet.</t>

        <t>The DHCPv6-Options Attribute is structured as follows:</t>

        <t>Type<list style="empty">
            <t>245</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Length<list style="empty">
            <t>This field indicates the total length, in octets, of all fields
            of this attribute, including the Type, Length, Extended-Type, and
            "Value".</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Extended-Type<list style="empty">
            <t>TBA1 (see <xref target="IANA-Att"></xref>).</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Value<list style="empty">
            <t>This field contains a list of DHCPv6 options (Section 21 of
            <xref target="RFC8415"></xref>). Multiple instances of the same
            DHCPv6 option MAY be included. If an option appears multiple
            times, each instance is considered separate and the data areas of
            the options MUST NOT be concatenated or otherwise combined.
            Consistent with Section 17 of <xref target="RFC7227"></xref>, this
            document does not impose any option order when multiple options
            are present. <vspace blankLines="1" /></t>

            <t>Permitted DHCPv6 options in the DHCPv6-Options Attribute are
            maintained by IANA in the registry created in <xref
            format="default" target="drv6-reg"></xref>.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>The DHCPv6-Options Attribute is associated with the following
        identifier: 245.TBA1.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="v4" title="DHCPv4-Options Attribute">
        <t>This attribute is of type "string" as defined in <xref
        section="3.5" target="RFC8044"></xref>.</t>

        <t>The DHCPv4-Options Attribute MAY appear in a RADIUS Access-Accept
        packet. It MAY also appear in a RADIUS Access-Request packet as a hint
        to the RADIUS server to indicate a preference. However, the server is
        not required to honor such a preference.</t>

        <t>The DHCPv4-Options Attribute MAY appear in a RADIUS CoA-Request
        packet.</t>

        <t>The DHCPv4-Options Attribute MAY appear in a RADIUS
        Accounting-Request packet.</t>

        <t>The DHCPv4-Options Attribute MUST NOT appear in any other RADIUS
        packet.</t>

        <t>The DHCPv4-Options Attribute is structured as follows:</t>

        <t>Type<list style="empty">
            <t>245</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Length<list style="empty">
            <t>This field indicates the total length, in octets, of all fields
            of this attribute, including the Type, Length, Extended-Type, and
            "Value".</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Extended-Type<list style="empty">
            <t>TBA2 (see <xref target="IANA-Att"></xref>).</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Value<list style="empty">
            <t>This field contains a list of DHCPv4 options. Multiple
            instances of the same DHCPv4 option MAY be included, especially
            for concatenation-requiring options that exceed the maximum DHCPv4
            option size of 255 octets. The mechanism specified in <xref
            target="RFC3396"></xref> MUST be used for splitting and
            concatenating the instances of a concatenation-requiring
            option.<vspace blankLines="1" />Permitted DHCPv4 options in the
            DHCPv4-Options Attribute are maintained by IANA in the registry
            created in <xref format="default" target="drv4-reg"></xref>.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>The DHCPv4-Options Attribute is associated with the following
        identifier: 245.TBA2.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="RAD"
             title="Passing DHCP Options RADIUS Attributes to DHCP Servers">
      <section title="Context">
        <t>The RADIUS Attributes suboption <xref target="RFC4014"></xref>
        enables a DHCPv4 relay agent to pass identification and authorization
        attributes received during RADIUS authentication to a DHCPv4 server.
        However, <xref target="RFC4014"></xref> defines a frozen set of RADIUS
        attributes that can be included in such a suboption. This limitation
        is suboptimal in contexts where new services are deployed (e.g.,
        support of encrypted DNS <xref target="I-D.ietf-add-dnr"></xref>).</t>

        <t><xref target="update"></xref> updates <xref
        target="RFC4014"></xref> by relaxing that constraint and allowing to
        tag additional RADIUS attributes as permitted in the RADIUS Attributes
        DHCP suboption. <xref target="IANA-RAD"></xref> creates a new IANA
        registry to maintain the set of permitted attributes in the RADIUS
        Attributes DHCP suboption.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="update" title="Updates to RFC 4014">
        <t></t>

        <section anchor="update1" title="Section 3 of RFC 4014">
          <t>This document updates Section 3 of <xref target="RFC4014"></xref>
          as follows:<list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="OLD:"><vspace blankLines="1" />To avoid
              dependencies between the address allocation and other state
              information between the RADIUS server and the DHCP server, the
              DHCP relay agent SHOULD include only the attributes in the table
              below in an instance of the RADIUS Attributes suboption. The
              table, based on the analysis in RFC 3580 [8], lists attributes
              that MAY be included:<vspace blankLines="1" /><figure>
                  <artwork><![CDATA[           #   Attribute
         ---   ---------
           1   User-Name (RFC 2865 [3])
           6   Service-Type (RFC 2865)
          26   Vendor-Specific (RFC 2865)
          27   Session-Timeout (RFC 2865)
          88   Framed-Pool (RFC 2869)
         100   Framed-IPv6-Pool (RFC 3162 [7])
]]></artwork>
                </figure></t>

              <t hangText="NEW:"><vspace blankLines="1" />To avoid
              dependencies between the address allocation and other state
              information between the RADIUS server and the DHCP server, the
              DHCP relay agent SHOULD include only the attributes in the
              IANA-maintained registry (<xref target="IANA-RAD"></xref> of
              [This-Document]) in an instance of the RADIUS Attributes
              suboption.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="update2" title="Section 4 of RFC 4014">
          <t>This document updates Section 4 of <xref target="RFC4014"></xref>
          as follows:<list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="OLD:"><vspace blankLines="1" />If the relay agent
              relays RADIUS attributes not included in the table in Section 4,
              the DHCP server SHOULD ignore them.</t>

              <t hangText="NEW:"><vspace blankLines="1" />If the relay agent
              relays RADIUS attributes not included in the IANA-maintained
              registry (<xref target="IANA-RAD"></xref> of [This-Document]),
              the DHCP server SHOULD ignore them.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sample"
             title="Applicability to Encrypted DNS Provisioning">
      <t>Typical deployment scenarios are similar to those described, for
      instance, in <xref section="2" target="RFC6911"></xref>. For
      illustration purposes, <xref target="ex"></xref> shows an example where
      a Customer Premises Equipment (CPE) is provided with an encrypted DNS
      resolver. This example assumes that the Network Access Server (NAS)
      embeds both RADIUS client and DHCPv6 server capabilities.</t>

      <t><figure align="center" anchor="ex"
          title="An Example of RADIUS IPv6 Encrypted DNS Exchange">
          <artwork><![CDATA[+-------------+           +-------------+             +-------+
|     CPE     |           |     NAS     |             |  AAA  |
|DHCPv6 client|           |DHCPv6 server|             |Server |
|             |           |RADIUS client|             |       |
+------+------+           +------+------+             +---+---+
       |                         |                        |
       o-----DHCPv6 Solicit----->|                        |
       |                         o----Access-Request ---->|
       |                         |                        |
       |                         |<----Access-Accept------o
       |                         |     DHCPv6-Options     |
       |<----DHCPv6 Advertise----o    (OPTION_V6_DNR)     |
       |     (OPTION_V6_DNR)     |                        |
       |                         |                        |
       o-----DHCPv6 Request----->|                        |
       |                         |                        |
       |<------DHCPv6 Reply------o                        |
       |     (OPTION_V6_DNR)     |                        |
       |                         |                        |

                DHCPv6                     RADIUS]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>Upon receipt of the DHCPv6 Solicit message from a CPE, the NAS sends
      a RADIUS Access-Request message to the Authentication, Authorization,
      and Accounting (AAA) server. Once the AAA server receives the request,
      it replies with an Access-Accept message (possibly after having sent a
      RADIUS Access-Challenge message and assuming the CPE is entitled to
      connect to the network) that carries a list of parameters to be used for
      this session, and which include the encrypted DNS information. Such an
      information is encoded as OPTION_V6_DNR (144) instances (<xref
      target="I-D.ietf-add-dnr"></xref>) in the DHCPv6-Options RADIUS
      attribute. These instances are then used by the NAS to complete the
      DHCPv6 procedure that the CPE initiated to retrieve information about
      the encrypted DNS service to use. The Discovery of Network-designated
      Resolvers (DNR) procedure defined in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-add-dnr"></xref> is then followed between the DHCPv6
      client and the DHCPv6 server.</t>

      <t>Should any encrypted DNS-related information (e.g., Authentication
      Domain Name (ADN), IPv6 address) change, the RADIUS server sends a
      RADIUS Change-of-Authorization (CoA) message <xref
      target="RFC5176"></xref> that carries the DHCPv6-Options Attribute with
      the updated OPTION_V6_DNR information to the NAS. Once that message is
      received and validated by the NAS, it replies with a RADIUS CoA ACK
      message. The NAS replaces the old encrypted DNS resolver information
      with the new one and sends a DHCPv6 Reconfigure message which leads the
      DHCPv6 client to initiate a Renew/Reply message exchange with the DHCPv6
      server.</t>

      <t>In deployments where the NAS behaves as a DHCPv6 relay agent, the
      procedure discussed in <xref section="3" target="RFC7037"></xref> can be
      followed. To that aim, <xref target="urd"></xref> updates the "RADIUS
      Attributes Permitted in DHCPv6 RADIUS Option" registry (<xref
      target="DHCP-RADIUS"></xref>). CoA-Requests can be used following the
      procedure specified in <xref target="RFC6977"></xref>.</t>

      <t><xref target="ex2"></xref> shows another example where a CPE is
      provided with an encrypted DNS resolver, but the CPE uses DHCPv4 to
      retrieve its encrypted DNS resolver.</t>

      <t><figure align="center" anchor="ex2"
          title="An Example of RADIUS IPv4 Encrypted DNS Exchange">
          <artwork><![CDATA[+-------------+           +-------------+             +-------+
|     CPE     |           |     NAS     |             |  AAA  |
|DHCPv4 client|           |DHCPv4 server|             |Server |
|             |           |RADIUS client|             |       |
+------+------+           +------+------+             +---+---+
       |                         |                        |
       o------DHCPDISCOVER------>|                        |
       |                         o----Access-Request ---->|
       |                         |                        |
       |                         |<----Access-Accept------o
       |                         |     DHCPv4_Options     |
       |<-----DHCPOFFER----------o    (OPTION_V4_DNR)     |
       |     (OPTION_V4_DNR)     |                        |
       |                         |                        |
       o-----DHCPREQUEST-------->|                        |
       |     (OPTION_V4_DNR)     |                        |
       |                         |                        |
       |<-------DHCPACK----------o                        |
       |     (OPTION_V4_DNR)     |                        |
       |                         |                        |

               DHCPv4                      RADIUS]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>Other deployment scenarios can be envisaged, such as returning
      customized service parameters (e.g., different DoH URI Templates) as a
      function of the service/policies/preferences that are set by a network
      administrator. How an administrator indicates its
      service/policies/preferences to an AAA server is out of scope.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>RADIUS-related security considerations are discussed in <xref
      target="RFC2865"></xref>. </t>

      <t>This document targets deployments where a trusted relationship is in
      place between the RADIUS client and server with communication optionally
      secured by IPsec or Transport Layer Security (TLS) <xref
      target="RFC6614"></xref>.</t>

      <t></t>

      <t>As a reminder, DHCPv6-related security issues are discussed in <xref
      section="22" target="RFC8415"></xref>, while DHCPv4-related security
      issues are discussed in <xref section="7" target="RFC2131"></xref>.
      Security considerations specific to the DHCP options that are carried in
      RADIUS are discussed in relevant documents that specify these options.
      For example, security considerations (including traffic theft) are
      discussed in <xref section="7" target="I-D.ietf-add-dnr"></xref>.</t>

      <t>The considerations discussed in Section 7 of <xref
      target="RFC4014"></xref> and Section 8 of <xref target="RFC7037"></xref>
      should be taken into account in deployments where DHCP relay agents pass
      the DHCP*-Options Attributes to DHCP servers. Additional considerations
      specific to the use of Reconfigure messages are discussed in <xref
      section="9" target="RFC6977"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Table of Attributes">
      <t>The following table provides a guide as what type of RADIUS packets
      that may contain these attributes, and in what quantity.</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[Access- Access- Access-  Challenge Acct.    #        Attribute
Request Accept  Reject             Request 
 0+      0+      0        0         0+      245.TBA1 DHCPv6-Options
 0+      0+      0        0         0+      245.TBA2 DHCPv4-Options

CoA-Request CoA-ACK CoA-NACK #        Attribute
  0+          0       0      245.TBA1 DHCPv6-Options
  0+          0       0      245.TBA2 DHCPv4-Options
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>The following table defines the meaning of the above table
      entries:<figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[   0  This attribute MUST NOT be present in packet.
   0+ Zero or more instances of this attribute MAY be present in packet.
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <section anchor="IANA-Att" title="New RADIUS Attributes">
        <t>IANA is requested to assign two new RADIUS attribute types from the
        IANA registry "Radius Attribute Types" <xref
        target="RADIUS-Types"></xref>:</t>

        <texttable anchor="ra" style="headers" title="New RADIUS Attributes">
          <ttcol>Value</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Description</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Data Type</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Reference</ttcol>

          <c>245.TBA1</c>

          <c>DHCPv6-Options</c>

          <c>string</c>

          <c>This-Document</c>

          <c>245.TBA2</c>

          <c>DHCPv4-Options</c>

          <c>string</c>

          <c>This-Document</c>
        </texttable>

        <t></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="urd"
               title="New RADIUS Attribute Permitted in DHCPv6 RADIUS Option">
        <t>IANA is requested to add the following entry to the "RADIUS
        Attributes Permitted in DHCPv6 RADIUS Option" subregistry in the
        "Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol for IPv6 (DHCPv6)" registry <xref
        target="DHCP-RADIUS"></xref>:</t>

        <texttable anchor="rd" style="headers"
                   title="New RADIUS Attribute Permitted in DHCPv6 RADIUS Option">
          <ttcol>Type Code</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Attribute</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Reference</ttcol>

          <c>245.TBA1</c>

          <c>DHCPv6-Options</c>

          <c>This-Document</c>
        </texttable>

        <t></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="IANA-RAD"
               title="RADIUS Attributes Permitted in RADIUS Attributes DHCP Sub-option">
        <t>IANA is requested to create a new sub-registry entitled "RADIUS
        Attributes Permitted in RADIUS Attributes Sub-option" in the "Dynamic
        Host Configuration Protocol (DHCP) and Bootstrap Protocol (BOOTP)
        Parameters" registry <xref target="BOOTP"></xref>.</t>

        <t>The allocation policy of this new sub-registry is Expert Review
        (Section 4.5 of <xref target="RFC8126"></xref>). Designated experts
        should carefully consider the security implications of allowing the
        relay agent to include new RADIUS attributes to this registry.
        Additional considerations are provided in <xref
        target="reg"></xref>.</t>

        <t>The initial content of this sub-registry is listed in <xref
        target="rad-new"></xref>. The reference may include the document that
        registers or specifies the Attribute.</t>

        <texttable anchor="rad-new" style="headers"
                   title="RADIUS Attributes Permitted in RADIUS Attributes DHCP Suboption">
          <ttcol>Type Code</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Attribute</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Reference</ttcol>

          <c>1</c>

          <c>User-Name</c>

          <c>[RFC2865]</c>

          <c>6</c>

          <c>Service-Type</c>

          <c>[RFC2865]</c>

          <c>26</c>

          <c>Vendor-Specific</c>

          <c>[RFC2865]</c>

          <c>27</c>

          <c>Session-Timeout</c>

          <c>[RFC2865]</c>

          <c>88</c>

          <c>Framed-Pool</c>

          <c>[RFC2869]</c>

          <c>100</c>

          <c>Framed-IPv6-Pool</c>

          <c>[RFC3162]</c>

          <c>245.TBA2</c>

          <c>DHCPv4-Options</c>

          <c>This-Document</c>
        </texttable>

        <t></t>
      </section>

      <section title="DHCP Options Permitted in the RADIUS DHCP*-Options Attribute">
        <t></t>

        <section anchor="drv6-reg" title="DHCPv6">
          <t>IANA is requested to create a new sub-registry entitled "DHCPv6
          Options Permitted in the RADIUS DHCPv6-Options Attribute" in the
          "Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol for IPv6 (DHCPv6)" registry
          <xref target="DHCP-RADIUS"></xref>.</t>

          <t>The registration policy for this new sub-registry is Expert
          Review (Section 4.5 of <xref target="RFC8126"></xref>). See more
          details in <xref target="reg"></xref>.</t>

          <t>The initial content of this sub-registry is listed in <xref
          target="drv6"></xref>. The Value and Description fields echo those
          of <xref target="DHCPv6"></xref>. The reference may include the
          document that registers the option or the document that specifies
          the option.</t>

          <texttable anchor="drv6" style="headers"
                     title="Initial DHCPv6 Options Permitted in the RADIUS DHCPv6-Options Attribute">
            <ttcol>Value</ttcol>

            <ttcol>Description</ttcol>

            <ttcol>Reference</ttcol>

            <c>144</c>

            <c>OPTION_V6_DNR</c>

            <c>This-Document</c>
          </texttable>

          <t></t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="drv4-reg" title="DHCPv4">
          <t>IANA is requested to create a new sub-registry entitled "DHCP
          Options Permitted in the RADIUS DHCPv4-Options Attribute" in the
          "Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol (DHCP) and Bootstrap Protocol
          (BOOTP) Parameters" registry <xref target="BOOTP"></xref>.</t>

          <t>The registration policy for this new sub-registry is Expert
          Review (Section 4.5 of <xref target="RFC8126"></xref>). See more
          details in <xref target="reg"></xref>.</t>

          <t>The initial content of this sub-registry is listed in <xref
          target="drv4"></xref>. The Tag and Name fields echo those of <xref
          target="BOOTP"></xref>. The reference may include the document that
          registers the option or the document that specifies the option.</t>

          <texttable anchor="drv4" style="headers"
                     title="Initial DHCPv4 Options Permitted in the RADIUS DHCPv4-Options Attribute">
            <ttcol>Tag</ttcol>

            <ttcol>Name</ttcol>

            <ttcol>Reference</ttcol>

            <c>162</c>

            <c>OPTION_V4_DNR</c>

            <c>This-Document</c>
          </texttable>

          <t></t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="reg" title="Guidelines for the Designated Experts">
          <t>It is suggested that multiple designated experts be appointed for
          registry change requests.</t>

          <t>Criteria that should be applied by the designated experts include
          determining whether the proposed registration duplicates existing
          entries and whether the registration description is clear and fits
          the purpose of this registry.</t>

          <t>Registration requests are to be sent to
          radius-dhcp-review@ietf.org and are evaluated within a three-week
          review period on the advice of one or more designated experts.
          Within the review period, the designated experts will either approve
          or deny the registration request, communicating this decision to the
          review list and IANA. Denials should include an explanation and, if
          applicable, suggestions as to how to make the request
          successful.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Thanks to Christian Jacquenet, Neil Cook, Joe Clarke, Qin Wu, Dirk
      von-Hugo, Tom Petch, and Chongfeng Xie for the review and
      suggestions.</t>

      <t>Thanks to Ben Schwartz and Bernie Volz for the comments.</t>

      <t>Thanks to Rob Wilton for the careful AD review.</t>

      <t>Thanks to Ralf Weber for the dnsdir review, Robert Sparks for genart
      review, and Tatuya Jinmei for the int-dir review.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2865'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6158'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8044'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8174'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6929'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8415'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8126'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4014'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3396'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8499'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6911'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5176'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8484'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7858'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.9250'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2868'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2869'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3162'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6614'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4861'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2132'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2131'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7037'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-add-dnr'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7227'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7930'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7499'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6977'?>

      <reference anchor="RADIUS-Types"
                 target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/radius-types">
        <front>
          <title>RADIUS Types</title>

          <author>
            <organization>IANA</organization>
          </author>

          <date />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="DHCP-RADIUS"
                 target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/dhcpv6-parameters/dhcpv6-parameters.xhtml">
        <front>
          <title>Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol for IPv6 (DHCPv6)</title>

          <author>
            <organization>IANA</organization>
          </author>

          <date />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="BOOTP"
                 target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/bootp-dhcp-parameters/bootp-dhcp-parameters.xhtml">
        <front>
          <title>Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol (DHCP) and Bootstrap
          Protocol (BOOTP) Parameters</title>

          <author>
            <organization>IANA</organization>
          </author>

          <date />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="DHCPv6"
                 target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/dhcpv6-parameters/dhcpv6-parameters.xhtml#dhcpv6-parameters-2">
        <front>
          <title>Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol for IPv6 (DHCPv6), Option
          Codes</title>

          <author>
            <organization>IANA</organization>
          </author>

          <date />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
